Guide to the Clarence Lexow Scrapbooks 1881-1930s (bulk 1890s) MS 3189
New-York Historical Society
Clarence Lexow scrapbooks
1881-1930s (bulk, 1890s)
New-York Historical Society
Ferris, Warren, active 1890s
MS 3189
4 Linear feet in 4 record cartons (21 volumes)
The collection holds 21 scrapbooks primarily containing newspaper clippings concerning the political career of Clarence Lexow (1852-1910). Most, and perhaps all, of the scrapbooks were compiled by Lexow's brother-in-law, William Ferris. Lexow was a New York State Senator from 1894-1898 and the clippings relate principally to subjects that Lexow was closely involved with: the Senate Committee's investigation into New York City police corruption, legislative actions leading to the consolidation of Greater New York City in 1898, investigations into trusts and restraint of trade, and legislation on civil service reform.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Arrangement
The arrangement opens with the 12 volumes explicitly compiled and indexed by Lexow's brother-in-law, Warren Ferris. These are followed by 3 volumes closely related in date range and subject matter to the first 12 volumes, then the final 6 volumes in chronological order. Titles in [brackets] were determined by the processing archivist based on a skim of the contents.
Biographical / Historical
Clarence Lexow (1852-1910) was born in Brooklyn, NY. His father was a German immigrant and Lexow studied abroad in Germany for several years in his youth. He graduated from Columbia Law School in 1872 and practiced briefly in New York City before moving to Rockland County, settling in Nyack in 1882. There he headed a building and loan association and became a trustee and corporation counsel for the town.
Lexow became active in politics as a member of the Republican Party. In 1887 he ran for elective office for the first time, losing to the Democratic candidate for county judge. He lost again in an 1890 run for Congress, but was eventually successful, winning election to the New York State Senate, where he remained from 1894-1898, the period most represented in this collection.
In the Senate, Lexow immediately took up a leadership role in an investigation of corruption and extortion by the New York City Police Department. He chaired the so-called Lexow Committee, formally known as the Senate Special Committee to Investigate the Police Department of New York City. The committee's proceedings are credited with leading to the loss of the Tammany Hall (Democratic Party) mayoral candidate in 1894.
In the later years of his Senate tenure, Lexow was a central player in the legislative actions leading to the consolidation of Greater New York City in 1898, investigations into trusts and restraint of trade, and legislation on civil service reform. He declined renomination in 1898, returning to his law practice, though staying involved in party politics. Lexow died of pneumonia in 1910.
(The above note was based on information primarily from Wikipedia, Lexow's obituary in the New York Times, and documents in the collection.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Katharine Morton Babcock Fulmor (Mrs. William Fulmor), April 19, 1950. Katharine was the daughter of Caroline Lexow Babcock and the granddaughter of Clarence Lexow.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes 21 scrapbooks, 18 of which clearly relate to Clarence Lexow's political career, with three less clearly related. Of the 18 scrapbooks, all but one include newspaper clippings that document Lexow's candidacies for office in the 1880s and 1890s, his work in the New York State Senate in the 1890s, and New York politics of the 1880s-1890s generally. The Lexow Committee's investigation into police corruption, legislative actions leading to the consolidation of Greater New York City in 1898, investigations into trusts and restraint of trade, and legislation on civil service reform are all major topics of the clippings. One scrapbook, titled "Trust Investigations, 1897" is an exception in this collection in that, rather than clippings, it holds other original documents related to the trust/restraint of trade matter, including Senate report, bills, typescripts of testimony, and more.
Of these 18 scrapbooks, 12 were compiled by Warren Ferris, Lexow's brother-in-law. These are designated as volumes 1-12 in the scrapbooks themselves and in the container list. A few of these 12 volumes are inscribed to indicate that Ferris was the compiler, and the consistency of format suggests that all 12 were prepared by him. Each of these includes an index to the scrapbook on loose sheets of Lexow's Senate stationery. It is uncertain whether Ferris, Lexow, or another contemporary compiled the other scrapbooks, but those all relate to Lexow and New York politics.
In addition to the above 18 scrapbooks there are three others dating from about 1881-82 that are not obviously related to Lexow, though he may have compiled them in connection with his law practice. These hold clippings related to various court proceedings and lawsuits.
Newspaper clippings.; Scrapbooks.; Governmental investigations -- New York (State); Legislators -- New York (State); Metropolitan government -- New York (State) -- New York.; Police corruption -- New York (State) -- New York.; Politicians -- New York (State) -- New York.; Restraint of trade -- New York (State) -- New York.; Trusts, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Lexow, Clarence, 1852-1910; New York (State). Legislature. Senate. Special Committee to Investigate the Police Department of the City of New York
- Volume 1, 1893-1894, 1930s (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN1)
  Scope and Contents
  Some newspaper articles from the 1930s are found inside the back cover of the volume.
- Volume 2, 1894 (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN2)
  The volumes dating from 1894-1895 are heavily oriented toward the Lexow Committee investigating the New York City Police Department.
- Volume 3, 1894 (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN3)
- Volume 4, 1894 (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN4)
- Volume 5, 1894-1895 (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN5)
- Volume 6, 1894-1895 (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN6)
- Volume 7, 1895-1896 (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN7)
- Volume 8, 1896 (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN8)
  This 1896 volume is heavily oriented toward legislation concerning the consolidation of "Greater New York."
- Volume 9, 1896-1897 (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN9)
  This volume is heavily oriented toward the Senate's trust/restraint of trade investigation.
- Volume 10, 1897 (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN10)
- Volume 11, 1896-1897, 1900 (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN11)
  This volume is heavily oriented toward the consolidation of "Greater New York." The bulk ranges from 1896-97, with only a few 1900 clppings.
- Volume 12, 1896-1897 (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN12)
  This volume is heavily oriented toward the trust/restraint of trade investigation and civil service reform.
- "Trust Investigation 1897" (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN13)
  Unlike the other scrapbooks, this volume holds documents other than clippings. Documents include Senate report; resolution and bills introduced; typescripts of relevant laws; clips and other data on sugar, tobacco, gas, and other industrial trusts; typescripts of testimony; Lexow's notes; and a couple of constituent letters to Lexow.
- [New York City Politics], 1897 (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN14)
- [Politics], 1893-1904 (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN15)
- [Surrogate Court clippings], 1881 (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN16)
- [Clippings of articles concerning various New York court cases], 1881-1882 (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN21)
- [Lawsuit clippings], circa 1881 (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN17)
- [Politics, especially in relation to Lexow], 1887-1891 (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN18)
- [Politics, especially in relation to Lexow], 1891-1892 (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN19)
- [Politics, especially in relation to Lexow], 1892-1896 (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN20)